All right, so today's דף daf is י"ג Yud Gimmel and we're
in the middle of figuring out the critical moment for when you
look at the development of the wheat or the fruit or the
vegetables in order to determine which year they go by. The year
is determined by the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah by the first of
תשרי Tishrei but and that determines which year in the שמטה Shmita
cycle it is whether you can take from one year on the
next but the question is what stage of development are we looking
at? So to remind you the you know by the vegetables we
taught a clear ברייתא braita that taught about picking vegetables before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah and after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and that it
was the moment the critical moment was when it was picked. In
the גמרא Gemara we turned to you know let's just read the
one line I won't reread the whole thing but if you look
back on י"ב עמוד ב' Yud Bet Amud Bet about eight lines
from the 10 lines from the bottom it says תנן התם Tnan
hatam התלתן משתצמח Haitolsan mishetitzmach
this fenugreek from the time it sprouts והתבואה והזיתים משיביאו שליש v'hatvuah
v'hazaysim misheyaviu shalish
and the grain and olives when they are a third ripe. By
the way what does this mean a third ripe? I was checking
the other day after this in this book by יהושע פליקס Yehoshua
Felix who people might know is the one who did all the
work on agriculture and the animal life flora and fauna in the
time of the משנה. Mishna. This is a book called החקלאות בארץ
ישראל בתקופת המשנה Hachakla'ut B'Eretz Yisrael B'tkufat HaMishna which is agriculture in
the land of Israel in the time of the משנה. Mishna. It
was a bestseller so
Amazon top of the Amazon list. Anyway
he says that הביאו שליש hevi'u shalish means I always thought it
meant a third ripe anyway he says it means that it is
its weight is a third of what its final weight will be
the weight of the grain which is makes it more quantifiable. Right.
So anyway yeah it's even hard to do probably by eye.
Exactly because what are you going to do start chopping things down
and right so apparently you had a sense. Anyway so so that
goes so that's a regular established measurement which is from the time
it's the third ripe and the גמרא Gemara says by the תצמח
titzmach by the fenugreek that it means תצמח לזרעים titzmach lizraim which
תוספות Tosafot says means that it means that the seeds are can
be planted and will sprout forth and תוספות Tosafot says that's the
point of הביאו שליש. hevi'u shalish. הביאו שליש hevi'u shalish means that
the seeds have developed in the grain that they are fit for
being replanted. So that's important conceptually. Now this idea of הבאת שליש
hava'at shalish
dominates in a couple of areas but I want to distinguish. I
want to first say one thing which is the case of this
משנה mishna which I'm going to bracket off and then focus. There's
one question as you might remember which is the question about when
is the stuff obligated in תרומות ומעשרות? terumot u'ma'asrot? And that has
two points. Number one is when can I go to the field
when is it even considered fruit you know or food? When can
I go just eat it and it doesn't it's not חייב chayav
even if I took תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot it wouldn't be effective.
It's not yet at that stage. That's the beginning period and then
there's the end period which is גמר מלאכה gmar melacha which is
when it's finished being processed. Between the beginning and the end I
can snack from it but I can't eat a אכילת קבע. achilat
keva.
After גמר מלאכה gmar melacha I can't even snack from it. So
for example the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha by the grain is you
put it in a pile and you moved it into the house
וייכנס פני הבית. v'yechanes pnei habayit. The גמר מלאכה gmar melacha by
the vegetables we learned the other day was that you bundled them
up or you filled up the vessel. Okay so that's in terms
of its obligation not the dating of it which year but when
is it considered like fully obligated in its מעשרות? ma'asrot? When does
that period begin? Okay and there the period is הבאת שליש. hava'at
shalish. Not only by grain but by everything. That was the תוספות
Tosafot I mentioned yesterday that the beginning of the משניות mishnayot in
מעשרות Ma'asrot talk about all these different stages. The you know the
grapes look like this, the olives look like this, these fruit look
like this, this looks like that. תוספות Tosafot says what are all
these what are all these different things? And תוספות Tosafot says all
of those are applications of the principle of הבאת שליש hava'at shalish
and how it would look like in different types of fruits and
vegetables. Okay but that is a principle my gosh. That's the idea
of and I want to bracket that off
okay. That's the idea of
חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot which start at הבאת שליש
hava'at shalish
okay. Before this time prior to that it's like nothing even if
you were to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot it wouldn't be effective
and it goes till גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. Okay during the period
from הבאת שליש hava'at shalish to גמר מלאכה gmar melacha if you've
taken it it works and you can snack from it.
Okay after גמר מלאכה gmar melacha well I guess let's do this.
After גמר מלאכה gmar melacha you can't even snack. No snacking. Okay
so גמר מלאכה gmar melacha would be something like you know making
it into a mound and bringing it into the house right וייכנס
פני הבית v'yechanes pnei habayit or by the vegetables bundling the vegetables
after you picked them etc. That's when you can't even snack and
הבאת שליש hava'at shalish that's the beginning of the משניות mishnayot in
מעשרות. Ma'asrot. in מעשרות Maasros that talk about all sort of all
the different signs of it for different fruits and vegetables. But everything,
fruits, vegetables, grains, everything goes by הבאת שליש hava'at shelish for this
issue of חיוב chiyuv of תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Okay, so I
said all of that. Is that pretty clear? That's to bracket it,
because that's not what we're going to be discussing, but it's confusing,
so I wanted you to understand that's issue number one. Issue number
two, which is what we are going to be discussing, is the
question not of where is the חיוב chiyuv of תרומה ומעשר, truma
u'maaser, but what year do you go by? What year? Right, for
things like שמיטה, shemita, מעשר שני, maaser sheni, מעשר עני, maaser ani,
right, those all the issues we've been talking about, what year do
you go by? Okay, which year of the cycle is it? And
taking from one year on the next, taking you know from חדש
על הישן, chadash al hayashan, on
ישן yashan etc. What year is the stuff part, right, what year
does it go by? Yes, that's clear, that's a different question. Okay,
that's it's defined by ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, 1 תשרי. Tishrei. But
what event is relevant? And here it's not like here that everything
is הבאת שליש. hava'at shelish. Here it matters what event is relevant.
So for ירק yerak we see the event is is לקיטה lekita
I guess, you know, it's picking the vegetables.
Okay, by תבואה tvua
it is הבאת שליש, hava'at shelish,
okay, a third, okay, whatever, a third of the way there or
whatever. Okay, by fruit we're going to see, by פירות peiros we're
going to see that it is going to be חנטה chanata
blossoming. Okay, and we're going to see a little bit later that
there's going to be a question of קטניות. kitnios. Okay, I'll I'll
leave קטניות kitnios in a minute, that's going to be the עמוד
ב amud beis of today's דף.
daf. Wait, Rabbi Winzer just take תבואה tvua for a minute with
הבאת שליש. hava'at shelish. Right. What if it is planted and is
growing in one year but doesn't reach שליש shelish until the next
year?
So it goes by the year in which it reaches שליש. shelish.
That is exactly the point of this. You look at when this
moment occurred. When this moment occurred, what year did it occur in?
And that will determine that that's exactly my point, okay? Good, good.
It's חייב chayav at this point whatever, but when I want to
know which year is it in the שמיטה shemita cycle?
So here are the symptoms and then this is a timing when
did that symptom indicating its status emerge.
This is a different area of הלכה. halacha. This is not the
question of what year it's part of, this is just the question
of when can I take, when can I take תרומות ומעשרות? trumos
u'maasros? Okay, and that goes by שליש shelish for everything. Everything goes
by שליש shelish when it's when I can take תרומות ומעשרות trumos
u'maasros from it, okay? That is not the question of what year.
That's why this is confusing. This is the question of is it
enough developed as a fruit that תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros is meaningful?
Okay, this is what year is it part of? Is it part
of the first year of the שמיטה shemita cycle, the second year
of the שמיטה shemita cycle, is it a שמיטה shemita year? If
it's this year I can't take it on another year, okay? So
this goes by different symptoms for the different things.
You know what confused me then also because doesn't doesn't מעשר maaser
also have to go by the year? Yes.
So it's not just the שמיטה- shemita in other words on the
left hand side of the board is what's the condition of the
fruit? No, no, no, it's not the condition.
It is, but here the condition is always the same, a third.
It's I'm asking a different question. In this case I'm asking a
question of Rabbi Winzer, if I go out to my field and
the fruit is super unripe and I take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros
early, does it work? And my answer is no, if it was
less than a third unripe it won't work. Rabbi Winzer, am I
allowed to go to my field and to eat my unripe fruit
and have a snack? Oh, yes. Can I eat my unripe fruit
and have a meal out of it? No. If it's reached a
שליש, shelish, no. If it's less than a שליש, shelish, yes. That's
answering those questions of is it developed enough so that it's obligated
in תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. This is answering the question Rabbi Winzer,
is this a שמיטה shemita apple or a year one apple? Should
I take this apple on an apple I picked two months ago
or not? So my question is, well if it's a fruit I'll
ask you when did it blossom, before or after ראש השנה? Rosh
Hashana? If it's a vegetable I'll say when did you pick it,
before or after ראש השנה? Rosh Hashana? Right, if it's grain I'll
say was it a third developed before or after ראש השנה? Rosh
Hashana? So this is a different question. This is a question of
which year is it part of. Alright, so that's why it's confusing.
People- so maybe I shouldn't have mentioned this at all, but I
just want- but I just felt like you know for your edification
there's another area of הלכה halacha in which everything is a
שליש. shelish. Oh gosh, that comes off. Anyway, but in terms of
what we're focusing on, we're focusing on what year is the stuff
relevant for and there there are different symptoms or different stages based
on what type of fruit we're dealing with. dealing with. Okay? Yes?
Pretty much. All right, let's move on. Yeah. Now, where did we
leave off? We left off that one the question is where do
you get this idea of a שליש? shlish? and one of the
proofs was or the last proof we left off was was that
the תורה Torah describes סוכות Sukkot at the end of the seventh
year. It says, חג... Chag... it says that it's סוכות, Sukkot, you
know what, let's just read it. All right, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this:
מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Let's pick up from there on
י"ב עמוד ב'. Yod Bet Amud Bet. Eight lines from the bottom.
A little re-reading, but whatever, we need for context. מנא הני מילי?
Mena hani mili? אמר אביי אמר רבי יוחנן ומטי בה משמיה דרבי
יוסי הגלילי. Amar Abaye amar Rabbi Yochanan umati bah mishmei deRabbi Yosi
HaGlili. אמר קרא: Amar kra: so where do you know that a
third is significant by grain, at least for determining which year it's
part of? So he says the verse says: מקץ שבע שנים במועד
שנת השמיטה בחג הסוכות. Miketz sheva shanim bemoed shnat hashmitah beChag haSukkot.
So in the end of seven years on שמיטה Shmita on the
חג Chag of סוכות. Sukkot. But at the end of seven years,
so the גמרא Gemara says: שנת השמיטה מאי עבידתיה? Shnat haShmita mai
avidteh? Why are you calling it a שמיטה Shmita year? It's at
the... it's after seven years! בחג הסוכות שמינית? beChag haSukkot shminit? By
the eighth year it's already סוכות. Sukkot. אלא לומר לך Ella lomar
lach to tell you: כל תבואה שהביאה שליש בשביעית לפני ראש השנה,
Kol tvuah sheheviah shlish biShvi'it lifnei Rosh HaShanah,
if it was a third before it developed before ראש השנה, Rosh
HaShanah, אתה נוהג בה מנהג שביעית בשמינית. Atah noheg bah minhag Shvi'it
biShminit.
It will still have the status of the שמיטה Shmita year even
in the eighth year. So to show you, it calls the the
following year the שמיטה Shmita year because there are some laws of
שמיטה Shmita that still apply on grain that grew before ראש השנה.
Rosh HaShanah. So the question is, okay, that tells you that it
could have started growth from before and have that sanctity. But it
doesn't tell you that the key point is having grown a third.
That's still not answered. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רבי
זירא לאביי. Amar leh Rabbi Zeira l'Abaye. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said to אביי: Abaye: ודילמא לא איירי כלל? Vedilma lo ayri klal?
וקאמר רחמנא תשמיט ותיזיל עד חג הסוכות? Veka'amar Rachmana tishmit vetizil ad
Chag haSukkot? It says first of all maybe it's not talking about
the sanctity of the fruit. Maybe it's just saying that even if
nothing grew before ראש השנה, Rosh HaShanah, the laws of שמיטה Shmita
go into the eighth year. You know, maybe an idea of like
מוסיפין מחול על הקודש mosifin mechol al hakodesh don't work the land,
don't do whatever until סוכות. Sukkot. So לא סלקא דעתך. Lo salka
daitach. That doesn't make sense. דכתיב: Dechtiv: וחג האסיף בצאת השנה. VeChag
haAsif betzeit hashanah.
And the... this is in שמות, Shemot, the festival of gathering at
the end of the year. מאי אסיף? Mai asif? What does it
mean gathering? אילימא חג הבא בזמן
אסיפה? Ilima chag haba bizman asifah? Festival that comes at the time
of the gathering, like you would think of the stuff you know
bringing it back in after it's been drying out in the field.
הכתיב Hechtiv the end of the verse says: באספך. Be'aspecha. It says:
וחג האסיף בצאת השנה באספך את מעשיך מן השדה. VeChag haAsif betzeit
hashanah be'aspecha et ma'asecha min hasadeh. Okay?
So it says when you gather in. So why does it have
to say אסיף asif at the beginning? אלא מאי אסיף? Ella mai
asif? What does אסיף asif mean here? קציר. Katzir. It doesn't mean
gathering in, it actually means harvesting, which is pretty funny because you
don't harvest grain on סוכות Sukkot time. Actually I was reading in
Felix, you know, the things you do harvest in סוכות Sukkot time
are things like the legumes, but you do not harvest grain. But
anyway, okay. So it means אסיף asif can also mean harvesting.
וקימלהו לרבנן Vekimlehu l'Rabanan and the rabbis have it established דכל תבואה
שנקצרה בחג Dechol tvuah sheniktzrah bechag if you...
if you're going to harvest it on סוכות, Sukkot, בידוע שהביאה שליש
לפני ראש השנה. Beyadua sheheviah shlish lifnei Rosh HaShanah. It was a
third developed before ראש השנה. Rosh HaShanah. So therefore וקקרי ליה בצאת
השנה Vekakrei leh betzeit hashanah and it's called at the end of
the year, which means that it is still connected to the previous
year. So based on this verse of וחג האסיף בצאת השנה, VeChag
haAsif betzeit hashanah, what we are learning out is: you're going to
harvest something on סוכות, Sukkot, and it's still considered to be connected
to the previous year. If you're harvesting it on סוכות, Sukkot, it
must mean it was a third developed the previous year. So something
that was a third developed, that is connected to the previous year.
The year... that is the year in which it's part of. So
if the year before was a שמיטה Shmita and was a third
developed, it has the sanctity of שמיטה. Shmita. So that's how we
get a third.
There's no late winter... there's no late... There...
in Israel not really, which is why the עומר Omer is you
know it's not onerous to wait for the עומר Omer because there's
really only the spring wheat. I don't know, there might have been
a small wheat... winter crop. Anyway, okay. So that's the proof. The
proof is that by סוכות Sukkot we're saying that the stuff you
harvest is connected to the previous year, and if you're harvesting it
on סוכות, Sukkot, it must have developed a third in the previous
year. So אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא. Amar leh Rabbi Yirmiyah
l'Rabbi Zeira. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah said to רבי זירא: Rabbi
Zeira: וקימלהו לרבנן בין שליש לפחות משליש? Vekimlehu l'Rabanan bein shlish lephachot
mishlish? I don't get it. Do the rabbis really know could figure
out the difference between a third and less than a third? Which
could either mean like, how could you make such a... why does
a little bit of a difference make a difference? Although that would
be funny, that could be a question you could ask anywhere. It
sounds more like, how can you extrapolate, you know, and know, oh
if you harvested it on סוכות, Sukkot, it must have been a
third by ראש השנה? Rosh HaShanah? What, like you know, you can
determine that with such precision? Like you know, how do you... how
can you be so precise? So אמר ליה Amar leh he said:
לאו אמינא לך? Lav amina lach? Haven't I told you before? לא
תיפק נפשך לבר מהלכתא? Lo tipok nafshach lebar mehilchata? Don't take yourself
out of the halakhic system. Like you know, don't sort of ask
undermining questions. כל מדת חכמים כן הוא. Kol middat Chachamim ken hu.
This is the whole way the rabbis worked with their... with their...
measurements. בארבעים סאה טובל, Be'arbaim saah tuvel, with forty סאה saah you
go to the מקוה, mikvah, בארבעים סאה חסר קורטוב, Be'arbaim saah chasar
kortav, forty סאה saah minus a thumbnail, תוספות Tosafos says even minus
a drop, אינו יכול לטבול, eino yachol litbol, it's not a good
size of a מקוה. mikvah. Then, כביצה מטמאה טומאת אוכלין, kebeitzah metameh
tumas ochlin, the size of an egg is the טומאה tumah of
foodstuff, it has to be the size of an egg. כביצה חסר
שומשום, kebeitzah chasar shumshum, the size of an egg minus a sesame
seed, אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, eino metameh tumas ochlin, it would not.
שלשה על שלשה מטמא מדרס, shlosha al shlosha metameh midras, three by
three טפחים tefachim is considered a piece of cloth that's fit for
sitting on for the טומאה tumah of sitting. שלשה על שלשה חסר
נימא אחת, shlosha al shlosha chasar nima achas, if you remove one
string, אינו מטמא מדרס, eino metameh midras, it's not. Now, how is
that relevant? That just tells us there's got to be a cutoff
point. But presumably the relevance is that all of these are based
on assessing certain realities of the world. For example, how do you
get forty סאה saah for a מקוה? mikvah? We say forty סאה
saah is the amount of water that it takes for a person
to cover himself in that covers the entire body. So I could
say, what do you mean, have you measured every single person in
the universe? Do you know the exact
forty סאה? saah? Maybe if you did a scientific study you'd find
that it would be thirty-nine point eight סאה. saah. Point is we've
taken an average and we figure out what it is and that
becomes the הלכה halakha even if we can't be like perfectly scientifically
precise. How about the idea of a ביצה? beitzah? That's based on
the idea of the amount of food that fits in a person's
gullet. So you say what, you know it's exactly a ביצה? beitzah?
Have you measured? Have you,
etc., etc.? We estimate, we do an average, and we do the
best we can, and then that becomes the size. And the same
by all of these. So the point is, stop, stop giving me
a hard time! This is how sizes work in all of הלכה.
halakha. We have an estimate of what that is equivalent to in
the real world and then that becomes formalized. So yes, a שליש
shlish becomes formalized. That's the amount we assume it has to be
in order to be able to be harvested by
סוכות. Succos. So that's one answer. Based on what can be harvested
by סוכות, Succos, based on a read of the verse, we retroactively
assume it had to have been a third before ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah.
Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. הדר אמר רבי ירמיה, Hadar amar
Rabbi Yirmeya, then רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya said, לאו מילתא היא דאמרי,
Lav milsa hi de'amri, the problem I was having with can it
really be a third, how do you really precisely know, forget the
question. It wasn't a good question.
דבעו מיניה חברייא מרב כהנא, De'ba'u minei chavrayah me'Rav Kahana, because there's
another basis to say, because there's other evidence to prove that the
rabbis really can figure out more or less than a third. What's
that evidence? דבעו מיניה חברייא מרב כהנא, De'ba'u minei chavrayah me'Rav Kahana,
the colleagues asked רב כהנא Rav Kahana the following question.
עומר שהקריבו ישראל בכניסתן לארץ מהיכן הקריבו? Omer she'hikrivu Yisrael bi'chnisasan la'aretz
me'heichan hikrivu? When בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael went into ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, they brought an עומר. omer.
It says, now where did they bring it from? What grain did
they use to bring the עומר? omer? They came in as we'll
see on the tenth of ניסן. Nissan. They brought the עומר omer
six days later. How could they use the grain that was already
standing when they entered in to bring the עומר? omer? Why not?
Let's take a look. אם תאמר דאייל ביד נכרי, Im tomar de'ayal
beyad nochri, it was grown by the non-Jews. They entered in and
it was stuff that had been grown and was growing before they
entered. קצירכם אמר רחמנא ולא קציר נכרי. Ktzirchem amar Rachmana velo ktzir
nochri. Only stuff harvested by you, not stuff harvested by the non-Jew.
So we're going to get to that.
So therefore we've got a problem. Now before we get to the
answer, the גמרא Gemara interjects. ממאי דאקריבו דילמא לא אקריבו? Mimay de'akrivu
dilma lo akrivu? I want to question the premise of your question.
You're assuming they brought the עומר. omer. Who tells you they brought
the עומר omer the first year? גמרא Gemara says no. לא סלקא
דעתך, Lo salka dachach, it doesn't make sense to say they did
not bring the עומר. omer. דכתיב, De'chsiv, because the verse says, ויאכלו
מעבור הארץ ממחרת הפסח מצות
וקלוי. Vayochlu me'avur ha'aretz mimacharas haPesach matzos vekalui.
They ate from the grain of the land from the day after
פסח, Pesach, the grain. So ממחרת הפסח אכול, Mimacharas haPesach achul,
the implication in the verse is they ate the day after פסח.
Pesach. מעיקרא לא אכול, Me'ikara lo achul,
beforehand they didn't eat from the grain of the land. So why
would there be a difference if they ate from the grain before
or after פסח? Pesach? What is the obvious difference? So what would
allow them to eat from the grain after פסח? Pesach? Why would
that be a key moment? דאקריבו עומר, De'akrivu omer, because they brought
the עומר, omer, which you bring on ממחרת הפסח, mimacharas haPesach, והדר
אכול, vehadar achul, and then they were allowed to eat the new
grain. So clearly the verse indicates that if they were only eating
the grain after ממחרת הפסח, mimacharas haPesach, it must be because they
brought the עומר. omer. Now, okay, fine, but that's true in the
פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, but the emphasis of ממחרת הפסח mimacharas haPesach seems
to indicate that. Now of course there are some questions with this
assumption. Number one
is, Michael says maybe it was just circumstantial, maybe just the מן
mon ran out. But number two is also the גמרא Gemara says
when you don't have a, if you don't bring the עומר, omer,
it becomes מותר mutar anyway, either at the beginning of the day
or the end of the day. So maybe they didn't bring the
עומר omer and it just became מותר mutar when the day ran
out. So that's another question. But the third question, which is I
think a really fascinating one, is one that תוספות Tosafos raises. Well,
okay, but before... Well okay, before I get to the third question,
let me also point out, you know there was the whole debate
with the Samaritans, what does it mean when the תורה Torah says
ממחרת השבת? mimochoras hashabbos? Does it mean, you know, when you bring
the עומר, Omer, does it mean the day after the first day
of יום טוב, Yom Tov, or does it mean the day after
the first שבת Shabbos after יום טוב? Yom Tov? So the interesting
thing is in some ראשונים, Rishonim, and the גמרא Gemara tries to
prove how it means after the first after the first day of
יום טוב, Yom Tov, but what the גמרא Gemara never says, but
some of the ראשונים Rishonim say, הרמב"ם HaRambam I believe, says the
best evidence is from this פסוק pasuk in יהושע. Yehoshua. It says
they ate from the grain on the day after פסח. Pesach. Doesn't
it say ממחרת השבת? mimochoras hashabbos? It says ממחרת הפסח. mimochoras haPesach.
So you see, it was the day after פסח Pesach that that
was significant because obviously that's what the תורה Torah means. It means
you bring the עומר Omer the day after the first day of
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it's interesting to note that this פסוק,
pasuk, which we're saying reflects the bringing of the עומר, Omer, then
becomes part of that evidence that the עומר Omer is brought the
day after the first day of פסח. Pesach. Then becomes an interesting
question which is what really does the word פסח Pesach mean? And
if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, it's always fascinating when
תוספות Tosfos quotes from like the Sephardi world. So every now and
then like you can count on the fingers of one hand the
number of times תוספות Tosfos quotes the רמב"ם. Rambam. Here might be
the only time that תוספות Tosfos quotes from the אבן עזרא. Ibn
Ezra. So you take a look. אקריבו עומר והדר אכלו. akrivu omer
vehadar achalu. Here's what תוספות Tosfos says. He says, הקשה
רב אברהם אבן עזרא. hiksha Rav Avraham Ibn Ezra. It's like he
was one of the בעלי התוספות. Ba'alei HaTosfos. He was like part
of their בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. He was a Sephardi, he was
the world of פשטנות המקרא, pashnut hamikra, you know, he never dealt
with פשטנות
הגמרא. pashnut haGemara. Same generation I think it was. What did you
ask? How much before תוספות? Tosfos? תוספות Tosfos is 13th century.
אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra was 11th, not 12th?
I think it was 12th. Yeah. So anyway, but it means that
somewhere in the אבן עזרא's Ibn Ezra's writing he raises this problem.
Okay. He doesn't mean that he asked the question to the other
בעלי התוספות. Ba'alei HaTosfos.
He had the manuscript.
Right. Had the manuscript. Right. So anyway, הקשה רב אברהם אבן עזרא.
hiksha Rav Avraham Ibn Ezra. הא ממחרת הפסח. ha mimochoras haPesach. What's
the day after פסח? Pesach? היינו ט"ו בניסן hainu tes vav beNissan
שהיא ממחרת שחיטת הפסח she'hi mimochoras shechitas haPesach הנשחט בי"ד hanishchat be'yud
daled כדכתיב בפרשת מסעי kedichtiv beparshas Masei ממחרת הפסח יצאו בני ישראל
ביד רמה. mimochoras haPesach yatzeu bnei Yisrael beyad rama. פסח Pesach in
the תורה Torah doesn't mean the יום טוב. Yom Tov. פסח Pesach
in the תורה Torah means the day of the bringing of the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. The holiday in the תורה Torah is called
not פסח Pesach but חג המצות. Chag HaMatzos. So ממחרת הפסח mimochoras
haPesach is the first day of יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's not
the first day of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Right? It's the day
after the bringing of the פסח. Pesach. So he goes through with
different types of answers. He says maybe it could also mean the
day after of after the eating of the פסח. Pesach. So maybe
פסח Pesach can also refer to the first day of יום טוב
Yom Tov because it could mean the day after. Yeah, but הלכתית.
halachically. Right. No you do because it's הלכתית halachically the next day.
So anyway, so anyway but I wanted to point out that interesting
thing. On the one hand this פסוק pasuk is used as evidence
that you bring the עומר Omer on the first day of חול
המועד, Chol HaMoed, and on the other hand it really hinges on
how you interpret the word פסח, Pesach, which you know makes it
all, you know, throws it all into question. But the גמרא Gemara
is clearly reading the word פסח Pesach as the 15th of ניסן,
Nissan, so ממחרת הפסח mimochoras haPesach is the 16th, and therefore that's
when the עומר Omer was brought and that shows they brought the
עומר Omer and that's what allowed them to eat from the new
grain. Yeah, Joe?
Two technical questions. One is, is bringing the עומר Omer מתיר matir
eating of wheat or only barley?
No, wheat, everything, all grain, all of the חמישה מינים. chamisha minim.
Okay, good.
And technically, the word רחמנא, Rachmana, we see this all the time.
People always translate it as the תורה Torah says.
Yeah, but technically it means God, right. הרחמנא. HaRachmana. Right. It's interesting
sometimes if you read the רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות, Peirush HaMishnayos,
before he quotes a פסוק, pasuk, he says, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, and then he quotes the פסוק. pasuk. Right.
רחמנא. Rachmana. Right. When one wants to say scripture, it says הכתוב.
HaKasuv. Right. So it is true, technically it means God says. Okay.
Because the עומר Omer wasn't barley, the עומר Omer was barley?
The עומר Omer was barley, but it's the bringing of the עומר
Omer allowed you to eat from all the
grain, all five types.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says okay, so they brought
the עומר. Omer. Where did they bring it from? If it was
grown, if it was harvested by the non-Jew, it would not have
been good to use for the עומר. Omer. So back to the
גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, so מהיכן הקריבו? meheichan hikrivu?
So אמר להם, amar lahem, so this is what רבי... Rebbi... whose
was it? Colleagues asked him? רב כהנא's Rav Kahana's colleagues asked him.
So אמר להם, amar lahem, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said back
to them, כל שלא הביא שליש ביד נכרי. kol shelo heivi shalish
beyad nochri.
No, what defines it as being non-Jewish harvest versus Jewish harvest, it
is this critical moment of a third developed. If it was a
third developed when it grew in the possession of the non-Jew, then
it's non-Jewish, then it has identified as non-Jewish harvest, non-Jewish grain. If
it got a third developed in the possession of a Jew, then
it's identified as Jewish grain. So they came into the land, the
grain was less than the third developed or some grain was, they
took possession of it, and then it was when it got to
be a third developed, it was identified as Jewish grain. Okay, so
again a third developed being critical. for its identity and what years
it related to what type of ownership is it related to and
so on. So that's his answer. Okay so now it says so
this is all quoted for רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yermiya to come to
terms with the fact that the rabbis could determine the difference between
the third and less than the third. So now רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yermiya says so that he says I know this whole discussion with
רב כהנה Rav Kahana ודלמא אתו ולא קים להו. Udilma atu velo
kim lehu.
So how did רב כהנה Rav Kahana how is that possible that
they went into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and they said oh look
here this grain is less than a third developed we'll use this
for the עומר Omer because it'll grow under our possession. How did
they know whether it was a third developed or not? אלא קים
להו. Ella kim lehu. It must be they were able to determine
whether it was a third developed. הכא נמי קים להו. Hacha nami
kim lehu. Here too they can determine it. Okay so that by
the way sounds like his real question was just how can you
identify whether it has satisfied the criteria or not the criterion right?
It doesn't sound like how did you come up with the criteria
which seemed to be the question. The question seems to be how
do you know if you've satisfied the criteria? And he says look
according to רב כהנה Rav Kahana when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael went
in the time of יהושע Yehoshua they were able to identify whether
it was a third developed or not so it must be we
can satisfy. Okay now that is not a source for the idea
of a third developed. That assertion about the עומר Omer assumes we
already know the principle of a third developed and it's applying it
to that story of the עומר. Omer. So right now what do
we have? We have that we learned out the idea of a
third developed from the idea of things that you harvest in סוכות
Sukkot where a third developed before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah based on
the פסוק Pasuk of סוכות Sukkot and we have an application of
the idea of a third developed to this story of the עומר
Omer and determining whether it was Jewish grain or not Jewish grain.
So we're going to finish the story of the עומר Omer and
then get back to the proof of or how do you determine
the idea of a third developed. Let's get back to the story
of the עומר. Omer. So it says like this ודילמא לא אתו
כלל. Udilma lo atu klal.
How do you know let's go back to the עומר Omer story
where do you get this idea that it was under a third
developed and that therefore it shows that they were able to determine
less than a third and more than a third? Maybe when they
came into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael there was some grain that had
not begun to sprout at all and that it totally sprouted completely
under Jewish possession. אבל היכא דאתו ריבעא בין שליש לפחות משליש לא
קים להו. Aval heicha de'atu riva bein shelish lefachot mishelish lo kim
lehu. Maybe if it's a quarter developed between a third and less
than a third you can't determine. Maybe it's not possible to ascertain
whether it's a third or a quarter developed. That piece you would
not be able to do. So you can't prove from there that
people are able to ascertain that. Maybe the reality at the time
of when they entered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was that it hadn't
sprouted at all and it totally sprouted under their possession. ודילמא לא
אתו כלל לא סלקא דעתך. Udilma lo atu klal lo salka datach.
That doesn't make sense that it hadn't sprouted at all. דכתיב. Dechtiv.
The verse says ויעלו מן הירדן בעשור לחודש. Vaya'alu min hayarden be'asor
lachodesh. They went up from the Jordan on the tenth of the
month. So they entered into the land only at the tenth and
they're eating from this grain right
on the sixteenth. ואי סלקא דעתך דלא אתו כלל Ve'ei salka datach
delo atu klal if by the time they entered into the land
it hadn't begun to sprout at all בחמישה יומי מי קמלי? Bechamisha
yomei mi kamli? How could it go from nothing to being fit
to be harvested in five days? So it couldn't be that it
hadn't developed at all. So it must have started to develop. It
was less than a third and it finished developing in the next
five days. But because it started to develop it's evident that you
can ascertain whether something is more or less than a third because
it's already started to develop. So the גמרא Gemara says I don't
understand how you solved anything. אלא מאי. Ella mai. So what do
you want to say? דאתו ריבעא או דנקא? De'atu riva o danka?
That it was a quarter or a sixth that's what a דנקא
danka means a sixth developed. So you say oh it had to
have started or else it couldn't have finished in five days.
אכתי בחמישה יומי מי קמלי? Akti bechamisha yomei mi kamli? Same question.
How does it go from being a quarter ripe to being fully
ripe in five days? You haven't solved the problem. Okay it's still
you know you gotta get it to do a lot of growing
in a few days. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי אית
לך למימר. Ella mai it lach lemeimar. What would your response be
to me if you said it was under a third developed and
it finished developing in five days and they harvested it and I
said how could it grow so much in five days? What would
you say back to me? You'd say ארץ צבי כתיב בה. Eretz
Tzvi ktiv bah. How is the land of Israel defined? As the
land of a deer. Now צבי Tzvi here means deer meaning the
it's alluding to a famous מדרש. Midrash. If you look at רש"י
Rashi five lines before the lines get wide רש"י Rashi says
ארץ צבי Eretz Tzvi מה צבי קל ברגליו מכל החיות אף ארץ
ישראל קלה לבשל פירותיה מכל הארצות. Ma tzvi kal beraglav mikol hachayot
af eretz yisrael kala levashel peroteha mikol ha'aratzot. The same way a
deer is very swift so ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the fruit ripens
quicker than all other lands. So the magical powers of Israel made
it ripen in five days from a quarter to complete. So that
would be how you would explain how it finished developing in five
days. So if that's what you're going to say from a quarter
to complete so I'll say the same thing. הכא נמי ארץ צבי
כתיב בה. Hacha nami eretz tzvi ktiv bah. Also it didn't begin
growing at all and it went from zero to a full in
five days. Okay so we leave that unresolved. Meaning again what have
we seen How do you know the idea that a third is
a significant criteria? Because it says חג האסיף, Chag HaAsif,
which is on the fifteenth of ניסן, Nissan,
of תשרי, Tishrei, which means here you are harvesting, that's how we're
reading the word אסיף, Asif, and if that's your harvesting and it
connects to the previous year, and here's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, then
we're saying before ראש השנה Rosh Hashana it must have been a
third. Okay, that's how we got the idea of a third. So
since you harvested it here and it's connected to the previous year
and we say it must have been a third, you see once
it's a third developed that determines the year it's connected to. That's
our source for the criteria of a third. This current discussion of
going into the land of Israel and bringing the עומר, Omer, yeah,
we'll make a s'ses on what the... you're harvesting your עומר, Omer,
okay, so it says that what's that relevant for? That's relevant not
for the proving the criteria but whether they can determine the criteria.
They entered in on the tenth, they brought the עומר Omer on
the fifteenth, on the sixteenth. It had to have grown under the
auspices of a Jew in order to be usable for the עומר,
Omer, which means that assuming we know the criteria of a third,
it means that it became that third which determines its identity under
the auspices of a Jew. So when the Jews are going in
here, I'll give them כיפות, kipas, okay? So when the concept of
the Jews are coming into the land of Israel, they are finding,
right, they are finding grain that is a quarter done, less than
a third, and then it is going to be it gets to
be a third under their possession so it's Jewish grain so it
could be used for the עומר. Omer. That's what we're saying and
they say, ah, so they're able to look at the grain and
see that a difference between more or less than a third. You
see you can apply the criteria. Right, and that's the... so the
discussion here was can you apply the criteria. They had to apply
the criteria to identify this as grain that was less than the
third. And the גמרא Gemara answers, no, maybe the grain hadn't grown
at all and they didn't apply the criteria and the entire grain
grew from zero to full during this period. And even though that's
magical, the whole thing is magical anyway so we might as well
make it more magical. Okay, so this was a discussion of can
you apply the criteria and the answer was not necessarily because maybe
they maybe it hadn't grown at all rather than saying it had
grown a little and they were able to apply the criteria. Now
we go back to this discussion of where do we know the
idea of a third from? Okay, so let's take a look.
All right, מתקיף ליה רבי חנינא. Maskif lei Rabbi Chanina. רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina asked, מי מצית אמרת, Mi matzis amris, back to the
idea of the criteria of this as the source for a third,
מי מצית אמרת, Mi matzis amris, how can you say דהאי
אסיף קציר הוא, de-hai asif katzir hu, that the word אסיף asif
means
harvesting, והכתיב, ve-hakasiv, the verse says, באספך מגרנך ומיקבך, be-aspekha mi-gornekha u-miyikvekha,
when you gather in to your granaries and your wine vats. So
obviously אסיף asif means gather, because you're gathering it in and you're
turning it into wine. ואמר מר, Ve-amar mar, and the master teaches,
בפסולת גורן ויקב הכתוב מדבר, be-piso shel goren ve-yekev hakatuv medaber, that
that's teaching you also what you make a סוכה sukka out of.
You make a סוכה sukka out of the remnants of the granary
and of the wine vats, like you can use the vines and
that type of stuff to make a סוכה, sukka, and if you
remember when we learned סוכות, Sukkos, that is one of the sources
that סוכה sukka has to be made, the סכך sechach has to
be made from stuff that grows from the ground and that is
not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because it says you use the leftover
stuff from the granaries and the wine vats. Now, okay, all that
is very wonderful, but what did you prove? Other than basically saying
the idea that the word אסיף asif in the simple sense means
gathering in and not harvesting, how have you challenged this interpretation? So
רש״י Rashi says the way it challenged it was the following. If
we learn from the word אסיף, asif, באספך, aspecha, the issue of
what the סכך sechach is made out of, then the phrase חג
האסיף, Chag HaAsif, if the word אסיף asif tells us what you
make the סכך sechach out of, then חג האסיף Chag HaAsif can
actually is another word for חג הסוכות, Chag HaSukkos,
right, do you understand, meaning if אסיף asif becomes the the key
term, the technical word to indicate what you make סכך sechach out
of based on this דרשה, drasha, then חג האסיף Chag HaAsif is
just a way of saying חג הסוכות, Chag HaSukkos, and therefore your
idea that the word אסיף asif is extra and doesn't mean gather,
it means harvesting, so we do the whole thing, nah, אסיף asif
just means סוכות Sukkos and therefore you don't have your whole דרשה.
drasha. Okay, besides it obviously wasn't פשט. pshat. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, so we've undone
this proof of a third based on אסיף asif as harvesting. So
says רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, האי מילתא הוה בידן, hai milsa hava
beyadan, oh, we had this thing in our hand, we had this
great דרשה drasha to learn out the idea of a third, ואתא
רבי חנינא שדא בה נרגא, ve-asa Rabbi Chanina shada beh narga, and
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina came along and threw a hammer in it,
okay, he threw a wrench in the works, we had a great...
Great דרשה *drasha* and he destroyed it. All right, now I need
to say a comment about this because that obviously is a very
graphic image. We had this great thing and somebody came and threw
a hammer in it, and it only occurs very rarely in ש"ס
*Shas*. And you know the other place it occurs in ש"ס *Shas*?
It occurs in סוכות *Succos* on the דאתיא מדרשא *de'asya midrasha* of
חג האסיף *hag ha'asif* בפסולת גורן ויקב הכתוב מדבר *be'psoiles goren ve'yekev
hakasuv medaber*. That when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in סוכות *Succos* learns
out from this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of חג האסיף *hag ha'asif* the
idea of that you can make סוכות *Succos* from the leftover stuff
from the wine vat and so on. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
well how do you know it doesn't mean that you can make
סכך *schach* from the actual fruit itself? How do you know, which
is מקבל טומאה *mikabel tumah*? How do you know it means the
leftover stuff? So it says no no no because it says wine.
You can't make a, you can't make סכך *schach* out of wine.
So then comes along רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* and says well maybe
it was frozen wine and that you could make סכך *schach* out
of it. So then says ach we had such a good דרשה
*drasha* and came רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* and he threw a hammer
in it. So it's quite fascinating that this idea of we had
a good דרשה *drasha* from this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* and somebody came
and threw a hammer maybe there was a question exactly what the
דרשה *drasha* was and what the hammer was because it's used in
one גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about a דרשה *drasha* about סכך *schach* and
it's used in this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about a דרשה *drasha* about
the idea of a third. Okay but where are we? We're at
the idea that we had this דרשה *drasha* of a third based
on reading this as harvesting, teaching us a third before ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*. Now we've completely thrown a hammer at it
and we lost that דרשה *drasha*. So we're back to the question
of where do we know the idea of a third? Okay so
אלא מנלן *ella minalan*? So where do we know it from? כדתניא
*kidetanya* like we taught in a ברייתא braita, *braisa* רבי יונתן בן
יוסף אומר *Rabbi Yonatan ben Yosef omer* ועשת את התבואה לשלוש השנים
*ve'asas es hatvuah lishlosh hashanim*. This is by the idea that there'll
be a jubilee year and you're going to say how can I
eat? I can't harvest for two years. What am I going to
do? There's a שמיטה shmita *shmita* year and a יובל *yovel* year.
And the תורה *Torah* says no God will send the ברכה *bracha*
and the year before will be very very plentiful and it'll make
three years' worth of grain. ועשת את התבואה לשלוש השנים *ve'asas es
hatvuah lishlosh hashanim*. So we're going to do a דרשה *drasha* on
that phrase. אל תקרי לשלוש אלא לשליש *al tikrei lishlosh ella lishlish*.
It'll make the תבואה *tvuah* for a third meaning once it is
a שליש shlish *shlish* it is עשוי *assui* it is complete. So
you got the דרשה *drasha*? Forget the complicated thing about it has
to be fit to harvest, blah blah blah. The דרשה *drasha* is
not related to the פשט *pshat* of the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* at
all ועשת את התבואה לשלוש *ve'asas es hatvuah lishlosh*. לשלוש
*lishlosh* becomes לשליש *lishlish* a third and it is finished, the תבואה
*tvuah* is considered complete once it is a שליש shlish. *shlish*. It
is done. And therefore we get the idea that a third for
grain determines when it is done. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says
והא מיבעי ליה לגופיה *ve'ha mibaye lei legupei*? What do you mean?
We need the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* to tell me the simple פשט
*pshat* that God is giving a blessing and the blessing is that
the grain will last for three years during the שמיטה shmita *shmita*
and the יובל *yovel*. Forget your דרשה *drasha* how about פשט *pshat*?
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says no כתיב קרא אחרינא *ksiv kra
achina* the other verse tells you פשט *pshat*. וזרעתם את השנה השמינית
ואכלתם מן התבואה ישן עד השנה התשיעית *uzratem es hashanah hashminis ve'achaltem
min hatvuah yashan ad hashanah hateshi'is*. It says you'll plant the eighth
year and while you're waiting for the stuff to grow you'll still
be eating from the stuff from the previous year. Or actually I
might have misquoted it might be ועשת את התבואה *ve'asas es hatvuah*
is not a jubilee year it might just be a normal שמיטה
shmita *shmita* year. I misquoted it because you still need it for
three years, you need it for the year it grew in, you
need it for the שמיטה shmita *shmita* year, and you need it
for the year that you're waiting to harvest the stuff in the
post-שמיטה shmita *shmita* year. Okay but anyway
the point is is that the פסוק *pasuk* already says explicitly that
God will give a blessing so you'll be able to survive on
the old grain even after the שמיטה shmita *shmita*. So what's the,
why does it have to repeat the three years? To tell you
this דרשה *drasha* of a third. All right so let's take a
breath. Okay so what we're up to now exactly am I losing
everybody or be— okay you're with me? Okay. So what we're up
to now is the idea that by grain it goes by a
third to determine which year it's connected to. We've also seen by
the way to determine whether it's considered Jewish wheat or not Jewish
wheat it goes by a third. And finally the דרשה *drasha* we
settle on is a simple not פשט *pshat* דרשה *drasha* but a
simple דרשה *drasha* of לשלוש *lishlosh* needs לשליש *lishlish* to mean לשליש
*lishlish*. And once it's a third done it's considered grain and that's
our idea that grain is a third. Now what we're going to
do now that we're done with the דרשה *drasha* is turn to
this part of the board and understand okay we got that grain
is a third. Where do you get all these other, what's the
other ideas for the other types of things? Vegetables by picking, fruit
is by blossoming, קטניות kitniyot? *kitniyos* we're going to get to. We're
going to talk about the different stages for the different types of
things. So let's take a look. The גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like
this: תנן התם *tenan hasam* we taught over there: האורז והדוחן והפרגין
והשומשמין *ha'orez ve'hadochan ve'hapargin ve'hashumshamin* so these are different types of legumes
rice and I don't know what דוחן *dochan* is millet and פרגין
*pargin* I don't know what that is שומשמין *shumshamin* is sesame. Papa?
Oh poppy.
Poppy was yesterday's notion.
פרגין *pargin* poppy. Okay poppy and sesame שהשרישו לפני ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah *shehishrishu lifnei Rosh Hashanah* if they took root before
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*... year seven, if they took root
then they're not שמיטה Shmita even if they continue to grow during
the שמיטה Shmita, year. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if they took root
after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, אסורין בשביעית, asurin bishvi'it, then if it
was coming into a שמיטה Shmita year then they would be שמיטה
Shmita produce and they'd have the restrictions of שמיטה shmita produce. ומתעשרין
לשנה הבאה, umit'asrin lishana haba'ah, and if it weren't a שמיטה shmita,
year, because on שמיטה years you don't take מעשר, ma'aser, if it
was a different year then the מעשר ma'aser would be following the
following year, not the previous year. So again this tells us ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah, is the determinant for which year it's part of.
But what does it tell us is the key moment for the
קטניות? kitniyot השרשה. hashrashah. Okay now that's a little bit bizarre, right?
Because all of these are stages of development. You know, שליש shlish
is a certain development, blossoming, okay it's starting to come forth, right?
Although it's probably less than a שליש. shlish, Okay, this is completely
done, but why this is like it's just getting started. So why
does this go by השרשה? hashrashah? It's not similar at all to
those other stages. And that's what the גמרא gemara is going to
ask. So let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so said רבא, Rava, and here's a nice
little summary. אמרו רבנן אילן בתר חנטה, Amru rabanan ilan batar chanatah,
the rabbis say a tree goes by when it blossoms. תבואה וזיתים
בתר שליש, Tvuah vezetim batar shlish, grain and olives go by a
third, okay, that's we've been focusing on that part. ירק בתר לקיטה,
Yerek batar lekita, these are the moments that matter, a vegetable goes
when it's picked. הני כמאן שוינהו רבנן? Hani keman shavinhu rabanan? These
things, these legumes and seeds,
which category is it like? It's not like any of them. Now,
okay, where's this idea coming of השרשה hashrashah and what's it similar
to? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so said רבא, Rava,
and רבא Rava answered his own question:
מתוך שעשויין פרחין פרחין, mitoch she'asuyin prachin prachin, because it's made in,
picked at various times. רשי Rashi says פרחין prachin is a word
used by legumes because it means like a עבודת הפרש?
avodat haparesh?
Well, you're constantly, endlessly, endlessly. Oh maybe, but רשי Rashi doesn't say
that, רשי Rashi says it means because you crack open the shells
of it, like the pods, but anyway but it means you're picking
them on an ongoing continuous basis. So therefore, עשו רבנן בתר השרשה,
asu rabanan batar hashrashah, the rabbis went by taking root. What does
it mean? It means if you had to say, forget the stage,
what are legumes most like? If you had to put them in
a category, we've divided the world into grain, fruit, and vegetable. Which
category would you put legumes into? Grain?
Really? Because they're like seeds, they're the kernels.
Okay, I would have put them into vegetables because I think peas,
I think vegetables. Anyway, but rice? Rice, that's true. All right, that's
true. But anyway, the way רשי Rashi says it is you would
have logically, this is what רשי Rashi says, concerning them a type
of a vegetable. But if it's a vegetable, it should be determined
by when you pick it. The problem is if you're picking it
on an ongoing basis, there's going to be in any normal circumstance
a mixture of stuff from before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. and after
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? It's not like it occurs like in
one fell swoop where either I picked
all the vegetables in from my garden before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
you know, or all the trees all blossomed either before or after
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah Here, because it's over a long period of
time and an ongoing basis, if we went by when you picked
it, it would be a whole mix of old and new stuff
and it would be very confusing in terms of תרומות ומעשרות. trumot
uma'asrot. So therefore the rabbis decided to make it easy for you
and they said when it took root, because you plant it at
the same time. So it all takes root at roughly the same
time, even though you pick it over a long period of time.
So is that clear? The reason is we want it to not
be confusing and a big mixture of pre and post ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah. so we're going to pick a moment that maybe it's
all done at once. So for legumes, the picking is over a
long period of time but the plantings all happen at once. Does
that answer? Now I want to stop for a moment and say
the point that רשי Rashi makes, which is: okay, because it's more
convenient to go by השרשה, hashrashah, we pick it because it's more
convenient? I mean, who gives you that latitude? Shouldn't it go by
a certain logical period of development? Right? Do you understand the point
that though it was convenient to go by השרשה hashrashah because it's
all the same time, who cares about convenience? I mean, shouldn't you
have to follow a rule? רשי Rashi says no, because קטניות Kitniyot
is all rabbinic. And since it's all rabbinic we can do whatever
we want. Okay, so basically we have this goes by taking root
because that's all the same time and this is all rabbinic. This
goes by שליש shlish, we focused on it. And I do by
the way want to point out again this issue about what's rabbinic
and what's biblical.
So ירק Yerek is rabbinic, that we know. קטניות kitnios is rabbinic.
So number one that it means is we have the latitude to
figure out, you don't have to ask what is the פסוק for
it, right? We can do whatever
we
want. The logic for this is we want it all to be
at the same time. We want to pick a moment where things
are done together and not things that happen over a long period
of time.
Why is there nothing distinguishable between them over the? Right.
What's the logic of here going by the picking, the time of
picking, not an earlier stage like we go by fruit and grain?
So רש"י Rashi says and the גמרא gemara will say that the
logic here is because it is constantly growing. And therefore, even like
right before you picked it, it's constantly growing, so it's not like
its primary related to a previous year. It's always related to the
year in which you picked it because it's constantly growing.
So it ripens it just gets bigger.
Exactly. Just gets bigger. Nicely way of saying that. Okay, now, then
so that's why that is. Okay, now, why is those are rabbinic?
This grain is biblical, okay, and that's why we have the פסוק
over here about a שליש, right? That's why he focused up here
about the שליש, we wanted a פסוק. The question again is the
issue of fruit. Is fruit biblical or rabbinic? Remember I told you
that debate the other day. If it's biblical, then there's a real
question of why the גמרא Gemara doesn't try to find a verse
for the fruit, right? It found a verse for this, why didn't
it try to find a verse for the fruit? Where do you
get blossoming? If it's rabbinic we don't need the verse. Now the
logic of blossoming is also the logic of like the when the
sap goes in the tree and when the sap is running, the
year in which it begins to blossom, it's continuing that's all of
the nutrients in which it's continuing to grow from, that's the year
it's connected to. That's the logic. Okay, but the question is what's
the source, you know, it's easier to say it's rabbinic and we
don't need a source because this is the only one the גמרא
quoted a source for. Okay, so these are the basic divisions, whether
they're biblical or rabbinic and what the logic is. Let's go back
now to the גמרא.
So that would be ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'Shvat, right?
Yes, and that's also going to be right. All of these are
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah? thank you. I put ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah,
up here, but we're going to have to look at fruit differently
as well because besides going by ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shvat. Right, right,
right. Besides going by blossoming and not having the פסוק, okay, so
here we don't know, is it biblical or rabbinic, we don't know.
Okay, but also this is the one thing that's going to be
ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat as the key moment and not ראש
השנה.
Rosh Hashanah
And
there's
a מחלוקת, machlokes, yeah, yeah, yeah, the verse to the... So we're
going to get up to that. Okay. All right. Is this confusing
enough? Back to the גמרא. Okay.
אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye said, I don't
get, just because you want things to be convenient that you're going
to make it by השוואה. hashva'ah. Why would it be such a
bad thing even if there was a big mix of stuff that
was picked before and after ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah, There's an easy
solution. What's the easy solution? ויצבור גורנו לתוכו. V'yitzbor gorno l'tocho.
Just pile up the threshing floor into its middle, meaning take all
the stuff, you're harvesting it and you're throwing it into your warehouse
or threshing floor. And now you've got a mix of old stuff
and new stuff, based on when it was picked. רש"י Rashi says,
I got a solution for you, make a huge pile, mix it
all together, and what's going to happen when you mix it all
together? Take תרומות ומעשרות trumos and maasros from the pile that it's
mixed. So any random ten percent that you take is going to
have an equal distribution of old and new, right? So if you've
got here your pile of קטניות that were picked before and after
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah and it's 40 percent old, right, and 60
percent new, but it's a good mix, and you go ahead and
you take your מעשר, maaser, okay, and let's say this is a
hundred units, okay, and you've now taken מעשר maaser of ten units,
okay, and you say this מעשר maaser is going to be on
this stuff. Oh, maybe you took on the old and the new.
No, because those ten units are going to be if they're equally
divided, four units of old and six units of new. And the
four units of old are going to go on the old stuff,
and the six units of new are going to go on the
new stuff, right? Is that clear? Forget percent. There are a hundred
units here. 40 old and 60 new. You'll take ten units and
you'll call it תרומות ומעשרות, trumos and maasros, and if that has
an equal distribution, then the four units of old will work for
the 40 units of old and the six units of new will
work for the 60 units of new.
There's no issue of ביטול bitul or...
Not ביטול, bitul, but the question is can we assume equal distribution?
הא מנה. Ha minah. Right. So no, not well, that's a good
question, but let's bracket that for a moment and ignore ביטול, bitul,
we're going to now focus on whether there's equal distribution.
Does he use to make an assumption that there's no...
Yeah, let's not talk about ביטול bitul just now. Okay, so אביי
Abaye says like this. ונמצא תורם מן החדש שבו על החדש שבו
ומן הישן שבו על הישן שבו. V'nimtza torem min hachadash shebo al
hachadash shebo u'min hayashan shebo al hayashan shebo. Whatever you take for
מעשר maaser will be equal distribution and the old part will work
for the old part and the new for the new and it'll
be the right percentage because it'll be equally distributed. מי לא תניא?
Mi lo tanya? Now of course you could still say it'll be
a problem because some will be pre-שמיטה and post-שמיטה, I mean some
will be שמיטה stuff and not שמיטה stuff. you know, or some
will be מעשר שני ma'aser sheni and some will be מעשר עני
ma'aser ani and you won't exactly know how to deal with it.
So this doesn't really solve everything, but this does solve the problem
of old and new but not of exactly if the next year
had different הלכות halachos than the new year than the previous year.
Anyway, let's take a look. מי לא תניא, mi lo tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, רבי יוסי בן כיפר Rabbi Yosi ben Kipar
אומרים משום ר׳ שמעון שזורי, omrim mishum Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, רבי יוסי
בן כיפר Rabbi Yosi ben Kipar
says in the name of ר׳ שמעון שזורי: Rabbi Shimon Shezuri: פול
המצרי, pol ha-mitzri, the Egyptian what is it fava bean thank you,
שזרעו לזרע. she-zara'o le-zera. Now that can be planted as a vegetable
and it can be planted for the seed. If it's planted for
the sort of for the actual vegetable part of it it goes
by when it's picked. If it's planted for the seed part then
we learn seeds and legumes go by when they take root. So
you've planted this to use the seeds, so it's going to go
by when it takes root. Okay so מקצתו השריש לפני ראש השנה,
miktzaso hishrish lifnei Rosh Hashanah, some of it took root before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah ומקצתו השריש לאחר ראש השנה, u-miktzaso hishrish le-achar Rosh
Hashanah, and some took root after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah and again
because it's for seeds it goes by when it takes root. אין
תורמין ומעשרין מזה על זה, ein tormin u-ma'asrin mi-zeh al zeh, you
can't take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-ma'asros from the stuff that took root
before on the stuff that took root after or vice versa לפי
שאין תורמין ומעשרין לא מן החדש על הישן ולא מן הישן על
החדש le-fi she-ein tormin u-ma'asrin lo min ha-chadash al ha-yashan ve-lo min
ha-yashan al ha-chadash because you can't take from old stuff to new
or new to old. So כיצד הוא עושה, keitzad hu oseh, so
you're stuck? No here's the solution. What are you going to do?
צוברו גורנו לתוכו, tzovro gorno le-tocho,
you put the pile of your thresh house in the middle meaning
you mix everything up together you bring it all together ונמצא תורם
ומעשר מן החדש שבו על החדש שבו ומן הישן שבו על הישן
שבו. ve-nimtza torem u-ma'aser min ha-chadash she-bo al ha-chadash she-bo u-min ha-yashan
she-bo al ha-yashan she-bo. So and it works out perfectly! So big
deal, you're telling me we got to go by השרשה hashrasha because
it'll be so impossible to go by having a mix of stuff,
old stuff and new stuff, there's a solution old stuff and new
stuff, you just mix it all together and שלום על ישראל. shalom
al Yisrael. Right. So again I do want to point out that
that's if your only problem is old and new. If the next
year is a different type of a year, one year is מעשר
עני ma'aser ani and one is מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, or one
year is not שמיטה the next year is שמיטה, not so simple.
But anyway this is the point, that there should be a solution
that should not push us to come up with a new idea
of taking root. Deal with it, it's a mixture, fine. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, so רבא Rava said back to אביי, Abaye, ר׳
שמעון שזורי גמרת? Rabbi Shimon Shezuri gemartah?
You're asking me from ר׳ שמעון שזורי? Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? ר׳ שמעון
שזורי סבר יש בילה. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri savar yesh bila. ר׳ שמעון
שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri holds that things mix, that you can have
not just liquids but you can actually have grains and solids that
mix and that it's going to be a completely equal distribution. רבנן
סברי אין בילה. rabbanan savri ein bila. The Rabbis don't agree.
Who says you're going to get an equal distribution? You know sure
there's forty and sixty units but any ten units you take could
be a random different distribution. So this trick will not work and
since this trick doesn't work we can't go by when you pick
because that'll be a whole mixture. We're going to go by when
it takes root. Okay. אמר רב יצחק בר נחמני אמר שמואל הלכה
כרבי יוסי בן כיפר שאמר משום ר׳ שמעון שזורי. amar Rav Yitzchak
bar Nachmani amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi Yosi ben Kipar she-amar mishum Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri. We actually rule that way, we rule that it goes
by, we rule that you can do this trick of mixing it
all together and that you can assume an equal distribution. Okay so
it is, and then it once again raises the question, so why
don't we go, so why did we have to go by when
it took root if you can do this trick and that's how
we פסק pasken the הלכה. halacha. But let's just read one more
sentence because it's not the end of the discussion. So the גמרא
says ומי אמר שמואל הכי? u-mi amar Shmuel hachi? So that statement
that we go like ר׳ שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri of יש
בילה yesh bila and mixing the stuff together was in the name
of שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא says, did שמואל Shmuel really say
that? והאמר שמואל, ve-ha amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says, לכל אין בילה
חוץ מיין ושמן. le-chol ein bila chutz mi-yayin ve-shemen. Nothing can be
considered to have equally mixed with the exception of wine and oil,
not together, okay, wine with wine and oil with oil. Okay, meaning
only liquids equally mix, other things don't equally mix. Okay, so how
can you claim that he says we go like ר׳ שמעון שזורי
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri that says it does equally mix? שמואל Shmuel explicitly
says that it doesn't. אשתמיטתיה. ishtamitayh.
What?
Did you just say it's not שמואל? Shmuel?
No but it was said in the name of שמואל.
Shmuel. אשתמיטתיה. ishtamitayh. Okay I'm sorry.
אשתמיטתיה. ishtamitayh. No so you forgot a third statement of שמואל Shmuel
like הכתוב השלישי המכריע ביניהם. ha-kasuv ha-shlishi ha-machria beineihem. בהא דאמר שמואל,
ba-ha de-amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel also says, הכל הולך אחר גמר פרי.
ha-kol holech achar gmar pri. It all goes by the end of
the by when the fruit finishes developing. What does that mean? It
means that שמואל Shmuel actually holds and the גמרא will spell this
out tomorrow I'll give you the quick version שמואל Shmuel actually holds
אין בילה, ein bila, things do not equally mix. That's like what
he said except liquids. So how does he say according to ר׳
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri if stuff took root before ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and stuff took root after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you
mix it all together and you can take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-ma'asros
because he doesn't hold that that works so that it mix, you
know why he holds that works? Because he basically says it doesn't
go by when it took root. It goes by when it finished
growing. So if you have stuff that took root before ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah, and stuff that took root after ראש השנה sure you
can take it all together because it all is next year. It
doesn't go by when it took root it goes by— So if
you have stuff that took root before ראש השנה and stuff that
took root after ראש השנה, sure you can take it all together
because it all is next year! It doesn't go by when it
took root; it goes by when it finished growing. So it's all
next year's fruit; it's not a mixture of fruit. So it is
really a very tricky, a very confusing thing to say. We rule
like רבי שמעון בן שזורי. Rebbi Shimon ben Shezuri. What he's really
saying is I totally don't rule that you could mix old fruit
with new fruit. What I say is in this case I consider
it all new fruit because I don't go by when it took
root; I go by when it finished and it all finished the
following year. Okay, so it's a pretty confusing way of articulating that
position. The גמרא will, if you're a little confused already, we'll go
back tomorrow and we will slow it down.
But then you're really mixing?
New fruit with new fruit! Or old, I mean I should say
old fruit with old fruit. Whatever you're mixing. Exactly! I rule like
רבי שמעון בן שזורי Rebbi Shimon ben Shezuri because I think in
his case it's not a mix. But you're not ruling like רבי
שמעון בן שזורי. Rebbi Shimon ben Shezuri. All right.